Bush-Brown Family Papers, 1835-1969
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Bush-Brown family papers
1835-1969
Bush-Brown Family
MS 26
16 boxes; 9 volumes; oversize materials (7.25 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Includes papers of sculptor Henry Kirke Brown; his nephew, sculptor Henry Kirke Bush-Brown; his wife, painter Margaret Lesley Bush-Brown); their daughter, artist Lydia Bush-Brown Head; and sons, Harold Bush-Brown and James Bush-Brown.
The principal subjects of the Bush-Brown family collection are: Henry Kirke Bush-Brown (1857-1935), sculptor; his wife Margaret (Lesley) Bush-Brown (1857-1944), painter; and their daughter, Lydia (Bush-Brown) Head (1887-1984), artist, designer. Also represented are their sons, Harold Bush-Brown (1888-1983), Professor of Architecture; and James Bush-Brown (1892-?), Landscape Architect; and sculptor Henry Kirke Brown (1814-1886), the uncle of Henry Kirke Bush-Brown.
The Bush-Brown Family Papers include correspondence, diaries, writings, books, original sketches, paintings, photos of artwork, and travel correspondence of Lydia Head from Europe. There is significant material related to the artwork of sculptor Henry Kirke Bush-Brown, painter Margaret (Lesley) Bush-Brown), and textile artist Lydia (Bush-Brown) Head. There is also a biographical sketch of Margaret Bush-Brown's father, geologist J. Peter Lesley. Correspondents include various family memebers, artist Ellen Day Hale, author Eliza Orne White, and others.
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
This collection has not been fully processed and therefore may be difficult to use.
History of the Collection
Lydia Bush-Brown Head donated her family's papers to the Sophia Smith Collection from 1968 to 1978.
Search Terms
The following terms represent persons, organizations, and topics documented in this collection. To find additional materials use these headings to search this web site, the Five College Library Catalog, or other library catalogs and databases.
Europe--Description and travel--Sources; Occupational therapy--History--Sources; World War, 1914-1918--France--Personal narratives, American; Hale, Ellen Day, 1854-1939; Brown family; Bush-Brown Family; Lesley family; Bush-Brown, James; Bush-Brown, Harold; Courtship--United States--History--19th century--Sources; Artists--United States--Biography--Sources; Women artists--United States--Biography--Sources; Family--United States--History--Sources; Sculptors--United States--Biography--Sources; Textile artists--United States--Biography--Sources; Bush-Brown, Henry Kirke, 1857-1935; Bush-Brown, Margaret Lesley, 1857-1944; Head, Lydia Bush-Brown, 1887-1984
Additional Information
Related Material
Additional materials relating to James Bush-Brown are at Temple University Special Collections. The Harold Bush-Brown Photograph Collection is at Georgia Tech Special Collections.
- Contents: finding aid (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Henry Kirke Brown
  - Biographical materials
    - "Henry Kirke Brown in Italy-1842-1846," The American Art Journal by Wayne Craven, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - "The Early Work and Development of Henry Kirke Brown" (thesis) by Octavia Hughes (Box 1)
    - "Life and Letters of a Sculptor Henry K. Brown" (manuscript), ed. by Henry K. Bush-Brown, circa 1934 (Box 1)
  - Photographs
    - Artwork (probably goes with "Life and Letters" manuscript above) (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - HKB and his studio, 1862-1866 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Henry Kirke Bush-Brown
  - Sculptures: photographs, 1887-1912 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
  - Invitation, certificates, sketch, and correspondence, 1908-30 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Biographical materials, notes, and articles, 1886-1935 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Pamphlets, correspondence, and articles, 1900-30 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - The Arts Club, Washington D.C.: pamphlets, clippings, correspondence, and photograph, 1918-27 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Exhibitions: pamphlets, correspondence, and article, 1922-31 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Photographs (D.C. home and studios), circa 1922 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Sculptures
    - "Indian Buffalo Hunt": Congressional bill, correspondence, clippings, and photographs, 1893-1943 (Box 3, Folder 8-9)
    - Medallions, plaques, etc.: photographs and clippings, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Projects: clippings, photographs, pamphlets, and proposals, 1926 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence
    - Caroline Bush (H.K.B.B.'s mother) to Lydia (her sister), 1866-1904 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Julia Bush (H.K.B.B.'s sister) and Caroline Bush, 1885 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Photographs (Bush family), 1866 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence from Henry Kirke Bush-Brown to
    - Henry Kirk Brown and Lydia (aunt and uncle), 1866 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Susan and Peter Lesley, 1885-86 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Lydia Bush-Brown (daughter), 1904-35 (Box 4, Folder 6-10)
    - Margaret Lesley Bush-Brown (wife), 1885-1929 (Box 5, Folder 1-10)
- Margaret Lesley Bush-Brown
  - Biographical materials: correspondence, notes, pamphlet, and clippings, 1923 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Diaries, 1872 [volume labeled 1869]-1903 (Box 6, Folder 2-4)
  - Address books and album, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Literary Society: minutes, 1926 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Lecture on "relations of women," 1901 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Notebook, notes, and correspondence, 1927-39 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Marriage certificate and list of wedding gifts, 1886 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Photographs, 1887-1928 (Box 6, Folder 10-11)
  - Artwork
    - Exhibitions: catalogues, lists, and articles, 1923-35 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Etchings, [see also Oversize Materials] (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Photographs of artwork, 1914-24, undated (Box 7, Folder 3-4)
    - Photograph album (MLBB and her works), undated (Box 7)
    - Miniatures by Margaret Lesley Bush-Brown, undated (Box 7)
  - Correspondence from M.L.B.B. to
    - Susan Lesley, 1885 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Margaret H. White and Eliza Drue White, 1889 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Henry Kirke Bush-Brown and family, 1921-22 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Henry Kirke Bush-Brown, 1907-26 (Box 8, Folder 4-8)
    - Lydia, 1904-29 (Box 8, Folder 9-13)
    - Lydia, 1930-44 (Box 9, Folder 1-3)
    - Family (during trip to England, Scotland, Ireland), 1914 (Box 9, Folder 4)
- Lydia Bush-Brown Head
  - Biographical materials: articles, clippings, and certificate, 1922 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Writings: memoirs (of Syria, Italy, Greece, Algonac (France), and Littlebrook), 1925-65 (Box 10, Folder 2-3)
  - Camp Fire Girls: articles, book, and calendar, 1914-29 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Artwork
    - Exhibitions: articles, pamphlets, and clippings, 1927-53 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Silk murals: exhibitions, articles and clippings, 1927-50 (Box 10, Folder 6-7)
    - Silk murals and watercolors: exhibition catalog, clippings and articles, 1943-61 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Photographs and patents, 1930-39, [see also box 12] (Box 10, Folder 9-10)
    - Silk murals: color scheme and notes, undated (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Christmas cards, 1928 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Paper dolls and costumes, undated (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Photographs, undated (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Shephards Nine - School of Dance: articles, undated (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Silk murals: photograph albums (2), 1917-, [see also box 10] (Box 12)
    - "Block Printed Samples of Gowns, Scarves, Cloakes from 1911 to 1918": sketchbook (Box 12)
  - Correspondence from L.B.B.H. to
    - Mary Ames (aunt), 1909 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Extracts of letters to family from France, 1918 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - James Bush-Brown (from France), 1918 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Henry Kirke Bush-Brown and Margaret Lesley Bush-Brown (from France), 1918 (Box 13, Folder 4-5)
    - Henry Kirke Bush-Brown and Margaret Lesley Bush-Brown, 1925 (Box 13, Folder 6-7)
    - Uncle Frank (from Europe), 1925 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Margaret Lesley Bush-Brown, 1929-37 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - Francis Head (from Mexico and California), 1928-32 (Box 13, Folder 10-11)
- Harold Kirke Bush-Brown
  - Articles by and about, 1888 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence to
    - Lydia, 1904-67 (Box 14, Folder 2-5)
    - Margaret Lesley Bush-Brown, 1909-20 (Box 14, Folder 6)
- James Bush-Brown
  - Articles by and about, undated (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Drawings, undated (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence
    - To Lydia Bush-Brown, 1938-67 (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Louise Bush-Brown (wife of James) to Margaret Lesley Bush-Brown, 1938 (Box 14, Folder 10)
- Malcolm Bush-Brown
  - Correspondence to (Box 14)
    - Lydia Bush-Brown, 1904-15 (Box 14, Folder 11-13)
    - Margaret Lesley Bush-Brown, 1904-14 (Box 14, Folder 14)
- James and Malcolm Bush-Brown
  - Play (manuscript): "Edith of Glenmire," circa 1901 (Box 14, Folder 15)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 14, Folder 16)
- General correspondence (most to Margaret Lesley Bush-Brown unless otherwise noted)
  - To Margaret and Henry Bush-Brown on their engagement, 1885 (Box 15, Folder 1-3)
  - ? Florence (and Lazare), 1884-85 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Ames, Charles Lesley (son of Charles W.; cousin), undated (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Ames, Charles W., 1876-82 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Ames, Mary Lesley: to Susan Lesley and MLBB, lectures, and typescripts, 1882-86 (Box 15, Folder 7-9)
  - Ashburner, Charles A., 1886 (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Boericke, William, 1882 (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Boyle, John J. and Bess, 1886 (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - Brooks, T. Benton, 1886 (Box 15, Folder 13)
  - Clements, Gabrielle D., 1884-85 (Box 15, Folder 14)
  - Crothers, Louise (wife of Samuel McCord), 1930 (Box 15, Folder 15)
  - Doggett, Lawrence L., 1919 (Box 15, Folder 16)
  - Deerfield Academy, 1934 (Box 15, Folder 17)
  - Delano, Catherine Lyman to Susan Lyman Lesley (sister), 1885 (Box 15, Folder 18)
  - Déson, Édouard, 1880-81 (Box 15, Folder 19)
  - Goldthwait, Joel E., Lt. Col. M.C. (extract from letter re: Lydia), 1918 (Box 15, Folder 20)
  - Gotch, J. Alfred, 1884-86 (Box 15, Folder 21)
  - Guinotte, Alfred and Laure, 1886 (Box 15, Folder 22)
  - Hale, Ellen Day, 1877-87 (Box 15, Folder 23-25)
  - Hall, James (American Geological Association), 1883 (Box 15, Folder 26)
  - Hallowell, Sarah C.F., 1884-85 (Box 15, Folder 27)
  - Head, E.L., 1882 (Box 15, Folder 28)
  - Hicks, Margaret, 1879 (Box 15, Folder 29)
  - Hill, Samuel, 1884-84 (Box 15, Folder 30)
  - Jackson, Anna (Philadelphia family friend), undated (Box 15, Folder 31)
  - Johnson, Eastman (painter), 1885 (Box 15, Folder 32)
  - Lesley, Peter: biographical articles and correspondence (to MLBB, HKBB, and uncles), 1844-87 (Box 15, Folder 33-36)
  - Lesley, Susan, 1823-1904, undated (Box 15, Folder 37)
  - Lesley, Susan to Margaret E. Harding, 1888-96 (Box 15, Folder 38)
  - Lesley, Peter and Susan: mementos, undated (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Lesquereux, Leo, 1885-86 (Box 15, Folder 40)
  - Lincoln, Robert, 1920 (Box 15, Folder 41)
  - Roosevelt, Sara Delano, 1938 (Box 15, Folder 42)
  - Smith, Richard S., 1882 (Box 15, Folder 43)
  - Thayor, Abbott A., 1882-86 (Box 15, Folder 44)
  - Volkenden, Karl, 1884-86 (Box 15, Folder 45)
  - White, Eliza Orne, 1881-85 (Box 15, Folder 46)
  - White, Lily, 1873 (Box 15, Folder 47)
  - White, Margaret E. Harding, undated (Box 15, Folder 48)
  - Lesley, J. Peter, 1819-1903 (Box 15, Folder 49)
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS
  - Henry Kirke Bush-Brown: photographs of sculptures (Box 16)
  - Etchings by Margaret Lesley Bush-Brown:"Ellen Day Hale" (1883) and "Fishing" (1885) (Map-case Flat file)
- BOOKS ON SHELF
  - Beaux Arts to Bauhaus and Beyond: An Architect's Perspective by Harold Bush-Brown, 1976
  - Garden Blocks for Urban America by Louise Bush-Brown, 1969
  - America's Garden Book by Louise and James Bush-Brown, 1943
  - Portraits of Philadelphia Gardens by Louise and James Bush-Brown, 1929
  - Life and Letters of Peter and Susan Lesley (parts 1 and 2)
  - Recollection of My Mother by Susan Lesley, 1889
  - A Little Girl of Long Ago by Eliza Orne White, 1896
  - Ednath and Her Brothers by Eliza Orne White, 1900